<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A poeme, on the Kings most excellent Maiesties happy progresse into Scotland, and much desired returne May. 1633.</title>
            <author>I. R., fl. 1633.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101921</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837724</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837724</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2064</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10293)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2064)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1033:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A poeme, on the Kings most excellent Maiesties happy progresse into Scotland, and much desired returne May. 1633.</title>
                  <author>I. R., fl. 1633.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[for F. Grove],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXXXIII. [1633]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: I or J. R.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles, --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2064:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2064:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A POEME, ON The KINGS moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent MAIESTIES happy Progreſſe into SCOTLAND, and much deſired returne.</p>
            <p>MAY. 1633.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at LONDON, MDCXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2064:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2064:2"/>
            <head>To all True-hearted Subiects, that wiſh well to our Gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne, His Royall Queene, Prince, Princeſſe, and State: The Authour, no Poet, but on this occaſion, directs his enſuing Poeme.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E's gone, the Sunne goes Northward, and t'was now</l>
               <l>Fit time of th' yeere; I'le tell you why, and how:</l>
               <l>Some in a Map doe trace each ſtep Hee makes,</l>
               <l>And with his Compaſſe one the diſtance takes</l>
               <l>From towne to towne, and, guided by his ſight,</l>
               <l>Dares to auouch that there He lay laſt Night,</l>
               <l>And here He din'd this day, and then, amain,</l>
               <l>He and his Troups paſſed ore ſuch a Plaine</l>
               <l>And ſuch a Meadow green, and fields that lay</l>
               <l>Cloſe to a Riuer running by that way.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2064:3"/>
               <l>Thus his Finger walkes the Iourney thorow.</l>
               <l>Laſtly he ſaith, This is Edinborough.</l>
               <l>Here muſt I point at things in generall,</l>
               <l>For that were infinite to touch them all,</l>
               <l>Or to deſcribe the wayes, or Townes, or woods,</l>
               <l>Or Hils, or Dales, or Fields, or dainty Floods</l>
               <l>And Brookes that glide along, I leaue that to</l>
               <l>Some other Muſe, for mine hath much adoe</l>
               <l>To finde a Clew of thred to lead her out:</l>
               <l>Of this great Labyrinth ſhe is about;</l>
               <l>Thus ſome take Pleaſure, and Recreation,</l>
               <l>To ſee Him in Imagination,</l>
               <l>To thinke they ſee Him preſent, heare Him ſpeake,</l>
               <l>As in a Dreame, though abſent when they wake:</l>
               <l>And whil'ſt they this contemplate, thus they ſing,</l>
               <l>No State ſo happy, ne're ſo ſweet a King.</l>
               <l>When they haue done in ſpeaking what they may,</l>
               <l>Vnto His praiſe, with bended knees they pray</l>
               <l>For Him and all that his Attendants be,</l>
               <l>Prayſing, and wiſhing their Felicitie,</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2064:3"/>
               <l>And that all bleſsings on His head may fall,</l>
               <l>To make His Royall race perpetuall.</l>
               <l>Marke how He mounts higher then Cancers Signe,</l>
               <l>And walkes with equall ſteps beyond that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Line
<note place="margin">The Geſts.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Which Phoebus ne're could paſſe,
<note place="margin">The Tropick.</note> His Tropicks ſtand</l>
               <l>Before the Sunne, take them by Sea or Land:</l>
               <l>Eaſtward He goes to France, and Weſt to Spaine,
<note place="margin">By Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Northward to Scotland, Southward backe againe</l>
               <l>To England, Royall Traueller; See here,</l>
               <l>H' exceeds the Sun, quarters the Hemiſphere;
<note place="margin">The Sunnes Summer beigne.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Now in His Apogaeum doth He ſhine</l>
               <l>Nine daies ith' North, more then ith' Sothern Clime.</l>
               <l>Aſtron'mers ſay 'tis common, yet miſtake,</l>
               <l>'Twas neuer but for Iames and Charles his ſake;</l>
               <l>See how Don Phoebus ſtriues for to exceed,</l>
               <l>Breathleſſe, and windleſſe, till his Courſers bleed,</l>
               <l>Drinks vp the Sea for thirſt, and lets it fall</l>
               <l>In Teares, into the Earths vaſt vrinall,</l>
               <l>And when he cannot compaſſe his deſire,</l>
               <l>With burning heat would ſet the world on fire;</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2064:4"/>
               <l>He riſes early, and goes late to bed,</l>
               <l>Yet ere one Moneth he yeelds, as vanquiſhed,</l>
               <l>Stands,
<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſtice.</note> gazing after him, and doth admire,</l>
               <l>But cannot moue, is forc'd for to retire.</l>
               <l>The Sunne, though glorious, needs muſt lay aſide,</l>
               <l>During this Progreſſe, all his glittering pride,</l>
               <l>Turnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Phoſphorus to our Phoebus all the way,
<note place="margin">The Day ſtar.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Serues for a morning Starre vnto the Day,</l>
               <l>And beares the Mace to Charles: See how goes</l>
               <l>And comes before his Maieſtie, and ſhowes</l>
               <l>As he aſcends to Northward, more and more,</l>
               <l>Great light to them that were all Night before.
<note place="margin">Dwellers vnder the North Pole.</note>
               </l>
               <l>But when the King returnes, the Sunne with ſpeede,</l>
               <l>Comes South againe, as if 'twere ſo decreed,</l>
               <l>They of th' Orcades riſe, and wondring ſay,</l>
               <l>They ne're obſeru'd it ſo ſince Iacobs day.
<note place="margin">King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ames.</note>
               </l>
               <l>For when of light they ſaw ſuch curious ſtreames,</l>
               <l>They did ſuppoſe it had been Phoebus beames,</l>
               <l>In hopes that he for his long abſence might</l>
               <l>Giue more then halfe yeere day; for halfe yeere night.</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2064:4"/>
               <l>Now they plucke on their clothes, awak't from ſleep,</l>
               <l>Reioycing much for to ſee the day peepe,</l>
               <l>One for his doublet, one for his breeches calls,</l>
               <l>Rowſing their Seruants from their Funeralls,</l>
               <l>Neere dead aſleepe: they that dwell fartheſt North,</l>
               <l>That for ſixe moneths at leaſt ne're ventured forth</l>
               <l>Of their owne doores, in haſte without diſpute,</l>
               <l>Run to the tops of th' Hills for to ſalute</l>
               <l>The riſing Sunne: by vſe the caſe is cleare,</l>
               <l>The firſt that ſees him ſhall be King that yeere.</l>
               <l>'Tis not your vſuall Sunne that now you ſee,</l>
               <l>But 'tis King Charles, a greater Sunne then he.</l>
               <l>Vp to your mountaine tops therefore, and pry</l>
               <l>For to behold him firſt as narrowly</l>
               <l>As e're you did your Sunne; who can alleadge</l>
               <l>The Conqueſt, ſhall not loſe his Priuiledge.</l>
               <l>When by Gods grace He ſhall returne, then we</l>
               <l>His loyall Subiects ſhall contend to ſee</l>
               <l>Our Souereigne firſt, no hills for this ſo high,</l>
               <l>As we deſire, no Alpes can ſatisfie.</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2064:5"/>
               <l>For when He tooke His Progreſſe, then each one</l>
               <l>That could not Him attend where He was gone,</l>
               <l>Looks at his Coach wheeles, as along they paſt,</l>
               <l>Striuing with greedy eyes to ſee him laſt.</l>
               <l>Thoſe of the Antarctike Pole haue cauſe to feare,</l>
               <l>The Arctick day will almoſt make a yeere;</l>
               <l>And they ith' night muſt all that while abide,</l>
               <l>Whereas the Sunne did commonly diuide</l>
               <l>The Day and Night betwixt them, good ſucceſſe</l>
               <l>Be to the Northerne world, th' Almighty bleſſe</l>
               <l>Denmarke and Swede, and all the reſt that are</l>
               <l>Confederates for that League, and German war,</l>
               <l>The Sunne comes neerer you, and gilds the Skie</l>
               <l>Till of your foes you get the victory.</l>
               <l>The birds moſt ſweetly chant it all the way,</l>
               <l>Bid him good morrow and good night each day:</l>
               <l>Each Wood and Groue, each Tree, and each Briar</l>
               <l>Yeeld Choriſters to make a dainty quire:</l>
               <l>Sometimes the Partridge one another call,</l>
               <l>Morning and Euening ſings the Nightingall.</l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2064:5"/>
               <l>T'were endleſſe to recount the Notes they ſing,</l>
               <l>When all the birds doe homage to the King;</l>
               <l>Vnder his window, ere the day appeare,</l>
               <l>Ioying and clapping crowes loud Chanticleere.</l>
               <l>Fiſhes and Beaſts doe th' like, but that my ſong</l>
               <l>Cannot aſſoord them roome, 'twould be too long,</l>
               <l>And o're the Hills and Valleys, with the bounds</l>
               <l>Of Horſes and Coaches the Echo ſounds,</l>
               <l>Repeating all thats done, or ſaid, as croſt,</l>
               <l>That any word, or tittle ſhould be loſt.</l>
               <l>The end for breuity by her expreſt,</l>
               <l>Shews that ſhe keepes a Iournall of the reſt.</l>
               <l>The highway Criples run by's Coaches ſide</l>
               <l>To aske an almes, which neuer is denied.</l>
               <l>You'ld laugh, how ſome, at th'end of euery towne</l>
               <l>With wooden legs will put the Footmen downe.</l>
               <l>The Maiors and Aldermen of euery place,</l>
               <l>And vnder-Officers, for a great ſpace,</l>
               <l>Come forth to meet him, and to offer vp,</l>
               <l>Some ſiluer Flaggons, ſome a golden Cup,</l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2064:6"/>
               <l>Some one thing, ſome another, any thing</l>
               <l>They iudge to be moſt pleaſing to the King.</l>
               <l>And thus in humble manner, as 'tis meet,</l>
               <l>Lay downe their keyes, and power at his feet.</l>
               <l>With them the rurall Lads, and Laſſes too,</l>
               <l>Staring and gazing to ſee what they doe.</l>
               <l>He's a deſpiſed clowne eternally,</l>
               <l>That comes not forth to ſee the King paſſe by.</l>
               <l>The Countrey Hoydens gaine thus much, they can</l>
               <l>That ſaw the King, write alwayes Gentleman.</l>
               <l>You'ld wonder how they'l boaſt, 'tis their glory,</l>
               <l>When to their ſweet-hearts they tell this ſtory.</l>
               <l>Sunne ſtand thou ſtill, and let thy Solſtice be</l>
               <l>So long ith' Heauen, till thou clearely ſee</l>
               <l>His ſafe arriuall, and returne againe:</l>
               <l>Leaue him not there, as once thou didſt in Spaine,</l>
               <l>Hoping to meet him, ſent with ſwift careere:</l>
               <l>Perchance, Expreſſe, to ſee how all did here.</l>
               <l>Our Sunne to Scotland gone, doth make our night,</l>
               <l>Our Moone His royall Conſort giues vs light,
<note place="margin">Queene Mary.</note>
               </l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2064:6"/>
               <l>Two pretty Starres increaſe it, that ſtand by</l>
               <l>Conioyn'd with her, Venus and Mercury.
<note place="margin">Prince Charles. Princeſſe Mary.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Marke a Parhelium now, two Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes for one</l>
               <l>Doe ſhine aboue our Northerne Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>izon,</l>
               <l>In Scotland one, in England one, yet the,</l>
               <l>So farre aſunder make a goodly day:</l>
               <l>And if thus diſtant they can ſhine ſo ſweet,</l>
               <l>How bright a Skie wil't be when they next meet</l>
               <l>His ſacred head all happineſſe attend,</l>
               <l>The Queene, the Prince, the Princeſſe, Subiects, Friend:</l>
               <l>Let Angels guardians, God Protector ſtand,</l>
               <l>By Sea His Pilot, and His Guide by land:</l>
               <l>By day His Cloud, by night His burning Torch,</l>
               <l>Nor cold by night, nor heat by day may ſcorch</l>
               <l>His royall Perſon; let His clothing be</l>
               <l>Eliahs Mantle, and His company</l>
               <l>Eliahs Chariot, Tobies Raphael</l>
               <l>Ith' way He goes; for thirſt giue Iacobs Well,</l>
               <l>For hunger Iacobs Veniſon, which may ſend</l>
               <l>A bleſſing to all thoſe that Him attend;</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2064:7"/>
               <l>For ſleepe giue Iacobs Pillow, at his head</l>
               <l>Set Iacobs Laddar, that which I haue ſaid,</l>
               <l>Giue all thoſe bleſſing which His conuoy found,</l>
               <l>Vnto our King for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o begirt him round.</l>
               <l>O let His ſleep be ſweet, His dreames diuine,</l>
               <l>Of heauenly angels, and his heart incline,</l>
               <l>Good God, that King Solomons dreame may be</l>
               <l>Confirm'd to Him and His poſteritie;</l>
               <l>And that in full aſſurance God may pleaſe</l>
               <l>Conduct Him ſafe, and bring Him backe in peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iuat Rex.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. R.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2064:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
